<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="topic11">
    <title>Viewing a Graphical Query Plan</title>
    <taskbody>
        <context>Using the pgAdmin 4 query tool, you can run a query with EXPLAIN to view the
            details of the query plan. The output includes details about operations unique to
            Greenplum distributed query processing such as plan slices and motions between segments.
            You can view a graphical depiction of the plan as well as the text-based data
            output.</context>
        <steps id="steps_q1h_kdn_vp">
            <step>
                <cmd>With the correct database schema highlighted in the object browser in the left
                    pane, select <b>Tools</b> > <b>Query Tool</b> from the top menu bar. You can
                    open multiple query tabs by selecting the option multiple times.
                    <image  href="../../graphics/pgAdmin4_queryDropdown.png" placement="break" width="679px" id="image_mjr_lxm_3bb"
                    /></cmd>
            </step>
            <step>
                <cmd>Enter the query by typing in the SQL Editor, dragging objects into the
                    Graphical Query Builder, or opening a file. Click on the lightning bolt and go
                    to the <b>Explain Options</b> in the dropdown to make sure the Verbose option is
                    not selected. (Verbose must be deselected to view a graphical depiction of the
                    query plan.) </cmd>
            </step>
            <step>
                <cmd>Click on <b>Explain</b> in the the dropdown menu to trigger the operation.
                    Note: The <b>Explain Analyze</b> function is not currently available with
                    Greenplum Database.</cmd>
                <stepresult>The query plan displays in the Output pane at the bottom of the screen.
                    Select the <uicontrol>Explain</uicontrol> tab to view the graphical output. For
                        example:<fig id="io149084">
                        <title>Graphical Query Plan in pgAdmin 4</title>
                        <image href="../../graphics/queryscreen.png" width="499px"
                            id="image_zjf_wk2_fbb"/>
                    </fig><p>You can also view the history of the queries you have run by simply
                        clicking on the <uicontrol>Query History</uicontrol> tab to view the
                        result.</p><fig id="fig_uwm_vwp_hbb">
                        <title>Viewing Query History</title>
                        <image href="../../graphics/pgAdmin4_query_history.png" width="499px"
                            id="image_el5_ywp_hbb"/>
                    </fig></stepresult>
            </step>
        </steps>
    </taskbody>
</task>
